<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-01-18T18:30:29-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Hussain Alafaireet</title><subtitle>Welcome to my personal website.  I host my portfolio here, and am planning to expand out with future project and my thoughts on various tech-related items.  Please feel free to look around!</subtitle><author><name>Email</name></author><entry><title type="html">Project: The Introducer</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/project/2018/01/12/Projects-The-Introducer.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Project:  The Introducer" /><published>2018-01-12T19:12:11-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-12T19:12:11-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/portfolio/project/2018/01/12/Projects-The-Introducer</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/project/2018/01/12/Projects-The-Introducer.html">&lt;p&gt;The project covers the design prototype I developed for my Fall 2017 Interaction Design class at the University of Michigan’s Master’s in Information Science program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-problem&quot;&gt;The Problem&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New university students face many personal challenges as they adapt to their new circumstances.  They often move away from their existing social network of friends and family, and into a complex and unstructured university environment.  Having little immediate common ground with others in their living spaces, and overwhelmed by demanding university class workload, students can feel alone, isolated, even in the midst of an apartment complex filled with other people.  My solution challenges this situation, and allows students to turn social barriers into opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-solution&quot;&gt;The Solution&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The target solution for this problem is a smartphone app called &lt;em&gt;“The Introducer”&lt;/em&gt;.  A user of this system will be able to use the app in conjunction with QR codes mounted on the door of another fellow apartment dweller.  Scanning the code will then let the user view a pre-recorded introduction of the resident, built by the resident themselves.  This will allow the user to get to know their neighbors in a convenient, low-stress way, while giving them knowledge that can be used to start a face-to-face conversation.  The application is gated by a login system controlled by the apartment complex administrators, which protects the safety and privacy of the apartment complex residents.  The intent is that the application is ultimately maintained by a third-party development organization, which whom apartment complexes can contract with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;design-tools-used&quot;&gt;Design Tools Used&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Storyboarding:&lt;/strong&gt;  Storyboard sketches were developed in order to create initial design demos that could be used to get user feedback.  The virtual introduction paradigm was selected by user feedback out of the 8 initial design ideas presented by the storyboard.  See below for the storyboard for the winning design, which was developed into &lt;em&gt;The Introducer&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/SI%20582%20FA%202017%20Storyboarding_Alafaireet._cropped.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Storyboard Screenshot #1&quot; /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Paper Prototype:&lt;/strong&gt;  After the storyboarding, a paper prototype of the selected virtual introduction solution was developed with notecards, pen, and post-it notes.  This paper prototype incorporated several potential design decisions, and was again placed out in front of potential users.  See below for a video demonstration of the paper prototype.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/RQMt7AfWpAw&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Digital Prototype:&lt;/strong&gt;  an electronic prototype was developing using the Axure prototyping toolset, with additional widgets from  the Axure iOS Flat Wireframe Template, UX Tool Time Android Template Library, and Flaticon.com.  Please check out the the developed Axure prototype at &lt;a href=&quot;https://ljnt81.axshare.com&quot;&gt;this link&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Email</name></author><summary type="html">The project covers the design prototype I developed for my Fall 2017 Interaction Design class at the University of Michigan’s Master’s in Information Science program.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Project: SI 501 Client Consulting Project</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/project/2018/01/12/Project-SI501-Client-Consulting-Project.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Project:  SI 501 Client Consulting Project" /><published>2018-01-12T19:12:11-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-12T19:12:11-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/portfolio/project/2018/01/12/Project-SI501-Client-Consulting-Project</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/project/2018/01/12/Project-SI501-Client-Consulting-Project.html">&lt;p&gt;The project covers the project I worked on for my Fall 2017 SI 501:  Contextual Inquiry class at the University of Michigan’s Master’s in Information Science program.  In SI 501, student teams act as consultants for real-world clients, using an analysis methodology called &lt;em&gt;Contextual Inquiry&lt;/em&gt; to investigate the clients’ problems and come up with solution.  I worked with 3 other students over the course of a four month project period, as a team called &lt;em&gt;3 Data Scientists and an HCI Guy&lt;/em&gt; (I was the HCI guy, by the way).  Together, we analyzed the client’s problem, developed recommendations, and presented them to the client.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;client-problem&quot;&gt;Client Problem&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our client was a local area non-profit organization focusing encouraging the efforts of local business to become more environmentally conscious.  The client organization had experienced a growth surge in recent years, and found it’s communication, documentation, and project management structure to be unable to fully manage the new team structure.  The organization was a virtual team, with remote team members in a variety of locations.  The decentralized nature of the team was an additional factor exacerbating the problems with the new team size.  The client wanted our team to review the organization’s current processes and tooling, and make suggestions to improve communication and project management within the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;analysis-methodology&quot;&gt;Analysis Methodology&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our analysis process was broken down into the following procedure steps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interviewing:&lt;/strong&gt;  Our team collected our base data via semi-structured interviews with the members of the client organization.  These interviews were the core of the Contextual Inquiry methodology, as they were not standard question-and-answer interviews.  Instead, our team took on the role of apprentices, having the interviewees walk us directly through their day-to-day work process.  We were thus able to see the daily processes, tools, documentation, and deliverables actually used by the organization.  This level of detail gave a wealth of data points about the organizations’ communication and collaboration issues.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;​&lt;strong&gt;Affinity Wall Analysis:&lt;/strong&gt; Our interviews gave us a wealth of data, but with only a limited amount of structure.  In order to organize our data, we used a technique known as an &lt;em&gt;Affinity Wall&lt;/em&gt;.  We wrote down individual data points onto Post-It notes, and then organized the notes based on connections we found by comparing the notes.  By adding summary notes to the emerging groups, and then repeating the process with the summary notes, we were able to drill down to the root findings behind the communication issues. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;  &lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/si_501_affinity_wall.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Affinity Wall&quot; /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;​&lt;strong&gt;Brainstorming:&lt;/strong&gt; Once we had determined the root causes of the issues, we brainstormed a series of potential solutions, and then ranked the solutions according to a set of criteria that included aspects such as feasibility, ease-of-use, cost, etc.  With this process, we were able to narrow down our list of solutions to three primary solutions:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;A collaboration plan, to formally define the communication/collaboration strategy.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;A recruiting plan, to ensure that new team members had skills the team really needs, including strong communication skills.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Slack tooling:  We noticed that our client was losing information due to the fact that their primary communication and information/archive tool was email.  We recommended moving day-to-day communications to a Slack server to create an archived, searchable communication environment.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;client-deliverables&quot;&gt;Client Deliverables&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we had our list of solutions, we developed both a final report and final presentation.  We delivered the report first, as the presentation session needed to be delayed due to scheduling.  When we presented, we found that our client had read our report already, and were in the process of implementing our recommendations!  My team is confident that we’ve made a real difference to our client, and that we’ve helped them solve the issues they had us analyze.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Email</name></author><summary type="html">The project covers the project I worked on for my Fall 2017 SI 501: Contextual Inquiry class at the University of Michigan’s Master’s in Information Science program. In SI 501, student teams act as consultants for real-world clients, using an analysis methodology called Contextual Inquiry to investigate the clients’ problems and come up with solution. I worked with 3 other students over the course of a four month project period, as a team called 3 Data Scientists and an HCI Guy (I was the HCI guy, by the way). Together, we analyzed the client’s problem, developed recommendations, and presented them to the client.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Project: Hololens Research Project</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/project/2018/01/12/Project-Hololens-Research-Project.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Project:  Hololens Research Project" /><published>2018-01-12T19:12:11-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-12T19:12:11-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/portfolio/project/2018/01/12/Project-Hololens%20Research%20Project</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/portfolio/project/2018/01/12/Project-Hololens-Research-Project.html">&lt;p&gt;I am current working on a research project with a University of Michigan faculty member.  We are trying to develop a  interface for the Microsoft Hololens augmented reality headset.  This new interface will give users the ability to manipulate Hololens virtual objects without knowing how to code or develop 3-D objects via the Unity game development editor.  This new interface will open up a level of augmented reality manipulation that those without Hololens development skills can’t currently access.  More to come on this soon!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Email</name></author><summary type="html">I am current working on a research project with a University of Michigan faculty member. We are trying to develop a interface for the Microsoft Hololens augmented reality headset. This new interface will give users the ability to manipulate Hololens virtual objects without knowing how to code or develop 3-D objects via the Unity game development editor. This new interface will open up a level of augmented reality manipulation that those without Hololens development skills can’t currently access. More to come on this soon!</summary></entry></feed>